<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Our research | Geocomputation and Earth Observation</title>
    <link>https://geco-group.org/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geco-group.org/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Our research</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 13:50:03 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geco-group.org/media/logo_hue21406914225b119becd577af1fb7f4d_583632_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Our research</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>MIND (SNF Eccellenza)</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 13:50:03 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/mind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The project MIND was funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation as a Eccellenza Fellowship (Grant No. PCEFP2_181115) and ran from Sep. 2019 - Aug. 2024. This page gives an overview of its outcomes. Work was conducted under three Objectives, described below.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lay-summary&#34;&gt;Lay summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The MIND research project investigated how carbon and nitrogen circulate in ecosystems, how water and carbon cycles are linked, and how forests respond to climate change. A key objective was to link the theory of eco-evolutionary optimality with various observations. To this end, we developed a new version of an ecosystem model that describes how plants adapt to their environment and how these adaptations affect the entire ecosystem. This model was then used to assimilate various observations, enabling more accurate and realistic simulations. In general, it was shown that observed changes in the structure and functioning of ecosystems are explainable and predictable, and that vegetation responds dynamically to changing environmental conditions. By combining theory, data, and modeling, MIND provides new insights into the behavior of terrestrial ecosystems. The results help to better predict how forests and other vegetation will respond to current and future climate change and how stable natural carbon and nutrient cycles will remain.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective-a-nutrient-controls-on-c-cycling&#34;&gt;Objective A: Nutrient controls on C cycling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under this objective, we compiled empirical data from diverse types of observations to quantify global rates of N cycling and to evaluate a next-generation ecosystem C-N model, informed by eco-evolutionary optimality principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work started by generating an estimate of the annual rate of total plant nitrogen (N) uptake and its global distribution—a key variable for improving our quantitative understanding of the N cycle. Previous estimates made incomplete use of available published data. Our re-attempt to quntify total global N uptake therefore provided a suitable starting point for the PhD student as it required us to compile published data on a set of related variables (terrestrial ecosystem net primary productivity, separated by plant compartments; C:N stoichiometry of different plant compartments, N resorption, net soil N mineralisation rates). This dataset was published separately (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10532099&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peng and Stocker, Benjamin, 2024&lt;/a&gt;). Our estimate (950 ± 260 Tg N year−1) for the total global N uptake is at the upper range of estimates based on model simulations (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.14208&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peng et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;). We also investigated the controls on global variations in N uptake and found that the relative allocation of biomass production in different tissues was a particularly important process driving variations in vegetation N uptake. The data compilation that on constituent variablels&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-global-distribution-of-n-uptake-figure-from-peng-et-al-2023httpsdoiorg1011111365-274514208&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Global distribution of N uptake&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/nuptake_peng_hu3c11dd87aca2547dd0684653b97e8a88_208123_b1568722e6703c4a638013f8952f89e6.webp 400w,
               /media/nuptake_peng_hu3c11dd87aca2547dd0684653b97e8a88_208123_a9c7d4213d2da789185a7d425ef8d857.webp 760w,
               /media/nuptake_peng_hu3c11dd87aca2547dd0684653b97e8a88_208123_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/nuptake_peng_hu3c11dd87aca2547dd0684653b97e8a88_208123_b1568722e6703c4a638013f8952f89e6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;380&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Global distribution of N uptake. Figure from &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.14208&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peng et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we targeted observations from ecosystem manipulation experiments and investigated how growth, allocation, C:N stoichiometry and photosynthesis respond to altered N inputs and elevated CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. Also here, we started by gathering published data from empirical work. To avoid duplication of efforts, we tightly coordinated work with collaborators and contributed to a publication of the MESI dataset—a comprehensive data compilation from ecosystem manipulation experiments, suitable for meta-analysis and model-data integration (&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/gcb.16585&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Van Sundert et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;). This dataset was published separately (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10423853&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Van Sundert et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;). We then proceeded to analysing results from CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; experiments with a focus on the coordination of responses in leaf photosynthesis and biomass. Our findings support neither control of leaf photosynthetic capacity (measured by V&lt;sub&gt;cmax&lt;/sub&gt;) by N supply, nor the N dilution hypothesis which posits that declines of leaf N content under elevated CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; are due to accelerated biomass production. They are however consistent with reduced leaf-level N demand in response to elevated CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (Peng et al., in prep.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results from this empirical analysis and the published perspectives paper on general principles and theoretical approaches for vegetation modelling by (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41477-020-0655-x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Franklin et al., 2020&lt;/a&gt;) guided the further development of a model for predicting the coupled carbon (C) and N cycling in terrestrial ecosystems based on eco-evolutionary optimality theory. The model, referred to as ‘CN-model’ (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.04.25.591063v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker and Prentice, 2024&lt;/a&gt;), constitutes a major output of this project. It provides a blueprint for translating the functional balance hypothesis—which posits that the balance of leaf vs. fine root growth is coordinated such that C assimilation and N acquisition are in the right balance for satisfying stoichiometric requirements—into a dynamic model of ecosystem C and N cycling, scalable for global-scale applications. Model code is currently available on Github (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stineb/rsofun/releases/tag/v1.0_cnmodel&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://github.com/stineb/rsofun/releases/tag/v1.0_cnmodel&lt;/a&gt;) and will be published on Zenodo upon publication of a peer-reviewed article. Insights gained from the empirical and theoretical work on coupled C and N cycling also provided a basis for reviewing the current state of global C-N models, their simulation of terrestrial C sink trends and how observed patterns can be translated into model implementations guided by eco-evolutionary optimality (Stocker et al., 2025b) (see figure below) and observed responses (grey bars) to increased CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, based on MESI data (&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/gcb.16585&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Van Sundert et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;). Modelled response ratios are based on the CN-model. Figure from &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/nph.20178&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al., (2025)&lt;/a&gt;.). The following general insights from this review are particularly important in the context of the project MIND: First, we found strong support for a shift in above vs. belowground allocation upon N fertilisation and elevated CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. Second, soil N availability has no influence on photosynthetic capacity (measured by V&lt;sub&gt;cmax&lt;/sub&gt;). Third, the atmospheric environment (temperature, humidity, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) influences leaf photosynthetic traits. Fourth, these general patterns found in the data are predictable from eco-evolutionary optimality principles and are accurately simulated by the CN-model (see figure below) and observed responses (grey bars) to increased CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, based on MESI data (&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/gcb.16585&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Van Sundert et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;). Modelled response ratios are based on the CN-model. Figure from &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/nph.20178&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al., (2025)&lt;/a&gt;.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-modelled-green-dots-and-observed-responses-grey-bars-to-increased-co2-based-on-mesi-data-van-sundert-et-al-2023httpsonlinelibrarywileycomdoiabs101111gcb16585-modelled-response-ratios-are-based-on-the-cn-model-figure-from-stocker-et-al-2025httpsonlinelibrarywileycomdoiabs101111nph20178&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;eCO2 meta analysis&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/eco2_meta_analysis_cnmodel_huebeb67508b2c52a685a6f16365d0c182_102301_e9266b96da193f6716afdfb334594ae3.webp 400w,
               /media/eco2_meta_analysis_cnmodel_huebeb67508b2c52a685a6f16365d0c182_102301_beb555596e54d40e293ba64de4b9be9d.webp 760w,
               /media/eco2_meta_analysis_cnmodel_huebeb67508b2c52a685a6f16365d0c182_102301_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/eco2_meta_analysis_cnmodel_huebeb67508b2c52a685a6f16365d0c182_102301_e9266b96da193f6716afdfb334594ae3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;474&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Modelled (green dots) and observed responses (grey bars) to increased CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, based on MESI data (&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/gcb.16585&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Van Sundert et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;). Modelled response ratios are based on the CN-model. Figure from &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/nph.20178&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al., (2025)&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work under the Objective Nutrient Controls on C cycling also provided synergies with other ongoing work in my group. The data from (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11071944&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker and Tian, 2024b&lt;/a&gt;) were used for &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.14208&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peng et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;, while related work on determining environmental vs. phylogenetic controls on leaf N, P, and N:P was carried out and published (Stocker and Tian, 2024a; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-49665-4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tian et al., 2024&lt;/a&gt;). Insights gained from the work on model-data comparisons and integration on the basis of ecosystem experimental data also provided material for the review by (&lt;a href=&#34;https://bg.copernicus.org/articles/20/3637/2023/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Caldararu et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;). The work on nutrient-carbon cycle relations informed contributions to several other publications to which MIND project members made contributions as co-authors (&lt;a href=&#34;https://bg.copernicus.org/articles/17/3511/2020/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Joos et al., 2020&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-021-01485-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ma et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;https://bg.copernicus.org/articles/21/4169/2024/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sophia et al., 2024&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective-b-water-limitation-in-a-changing-climate&#34;&gt;Objective B: Water limitation in a changing climate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under this objective, we investigated how vegetation sensitivity to droughts, its variations across space globally, its relations to rooting depth and topography and how to use eco-evolutionary optimality principles for accurate predictions of plant functioning under water stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work started with a focus on quantifying plant-available water storage and characterising water-vegetation activity relations using two different data types—ecosystem fluxes from eddy-covariance measurements for site-scale analyses and satellite remote sensing data for global scale analyses. For the site-scale analyses, we estimated the relative reduction in evapotranspiration due to root-zone moisture limitation. The approach taken relied on modelling a potential evapotranspiration rate using a deep neural network, trained on a moist-conditions subset of the data for each site, and contrasing it to actual evapotrantranspiration rates (code is made open access &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8186408&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Giardina, 2023)&lt;/a&gt;). This approach provided a new angle at detecting subsurface conditions (in this case water limitation) from aboveground measurements—available from a large number of globally distributed sites. Our results revealed a large variation in water stress relations across sites. While evapotranspiration rates were sustained at nearly their estimated potential rates despite long-lasting rain-free periods at some sites, evapotranspiration rapidly declined with increasing dryness at other sites (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19197&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Giardina et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;). These large variations could only partially be explained by commonly available site characteristics (vegetation type, soil conditions estimated from global soil maps, etc.). Our interpretation is that unknown subsurface structure (soil depth, groundwater table depth, bedrock porosity, etc.) is a major determinant explaining large variations of water stress relations across sites. This is an important result, indicating a major inherent limitation for modelling ecosystem fluxes across space—the modelling task addressed by Land Surface Models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-fractional-reduction-of-evapotranspiration-et-as-a-function-of-the-cumulative-water-deficit-cwd-across-sites-lines-the-color-of-the-lines-indicates-the-diagnosed-root-zone-water-storage-capacity-for-the-respective-sites-extracted-from-the-data-of-stocker-et-al-2023httpswwwnaturecomarticless41561-023-01125-2-figure-based-on-results-from-giardina-et-al-2023httpsdoiorg101111nph19197&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;evapotranspiration drydown at FLUXNET sites&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/fet_fluxnet_giardina23_hu6fdc59ad43ab8fa931015d0c76a9e527_326593_e08994a45ef609f64a828b66d11a0ff4.webp 400w,
               /media/fet_fluxnet_giardina23_hu6fdc59ad43ab8fa931015d0c76a9e527_326593_f1c1e721459ae7a4cfde75ea5e873a43.webp 760w,
               /media/fet_fluxnet_giardina23_hu6fdc59ad43ab8fa931015d0c76a9e527_326593_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/fet_fluxnet_giardina23_hu6fdc59ad43ab8fa931015d0c76a9e527_326593_e08994a45ef609f64a828b66d11a0ff4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;644&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Fractional reduction of evapotranspiration (ET) as a function of the cumulative water deficit (CWD) across sites (lines). The color of the lines indicates the diagnosed root zone water storage capacity for the respective sites, extracted from the data of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41561-023-01125-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;. Figure based on results from &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19197&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Giardina et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A complementary approach to quantifying water stress relations made use of satellite Earth Observation data. Instead of locally measured evapotranspiration, we used a data product based thermal remote sensing, which proved to yield reliable estimates also under dry conditions. The global analysis, performed at 0.05° (~5 km around the Equator) yielded insights that are consistent with the findings from (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19197&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Giardina et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;), showing a large variation of the (plant-available) rooting zone water storage across small spatial scales (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41561-023-01125-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;). Hence, variations of vegetation sensitivity to dry conditions arise not only across large climatic gradients and biomes, but also across smaller-scale topographic gradients. Again, we interpreted this as a reflection of the subsurface structure and hydrology and of the rooting depth of plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the global scale of the analysis, our map of the rooting-zone water-storage capacity—made available open access (Stocker, 2024b)—provides much needed information for specifying respective information in Land Surface Models, or for benchmarking state-of-the-art models as done in (Giardina et al., 2025). The work leading up to the publication of the global analysis by (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41561-023-01125-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;) in &lt;em&gt;Nature Geoscience&lt;/em&gt; spurred the development of a solution for efficient handling of big Earth Observation data for computationally demanding time series-based modelling. The respective code was published as an R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13356532&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Bernhard et al., 2025)&lt;/a&gt; and facilitated work for other projects &lt;a href=&#34;https://essopenarchive.org/users/1002365/articles/1362763-are-modern-droughts-unprecedented?commit=8b870a255912031cc36f3964c5d2a140bd44bcc2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Helpap et al., 2025)&lt;/a&gt;. Also the algorithm for calculating cumulative water deficit timeseries (from with the rooting-zone water-storage capacity is derived) has been implemented as an R package and has been re-used for other studies &lt;a href=&#34;https://essopenarchive.org/users/1002365/articles/1362763-are-modern-droughts-unprecedented?commit=8b870a255912031cc36f3964c5d2a140bd44bcc2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Helpap et al., 2025)&lt;/a&gt;, supervised Bachelor and Master theses, and teaching material &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12543104&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Stocker, 2024a)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the empirical basis developed in (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19197&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Giardina et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;) and (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41561-023-01125-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;, the simulation of water stress relations for modelling water and carbon fluxes was advanced in several studies. In &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41477-022-01244-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Joshi et al. (2022)&lt;/a&gt;, we developed a reduced-form representation of plant hydraulic relations and stomatal optimisation. Our theoretical approach was shown to accurately predict responses in several variables to soil dry-downs and is being further developed for simulating ecosystem carbon and water fluxes (Joshi et al., in prep.). The work on water-carbon cycle relations and drought impact detection and prediction informed contributions to several other publications to which MIND project members made contributions as co-authors (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2022/08/17/2022.08.16.504173&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kladny et al., 2024&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;https://bg.copernicus.org/articles/19/4315/2022/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Yu et al., 2022&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective-c-scaling-from-trees-to-the-forest&#34;&gt;Objective C: Scaling from trees to the forest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under this objective, we investigated how forest dynamics interact with tree growth and how previously untapped data resources can be used to achieve a data-informed simulations of forest dynamics in response to a chaning environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started by gathering data from unmanaged forests in Switzerland to quantify changes in the self-thinning relationship—addressing the question of whether forests are thickening. The self-thinning relationship describes how the number of trees in a forest stand declines as the average size of trees in that stand increases over the course of stand development and maturation. The data we gathered clearly reflects this relationship. There is an upper “edge” beyond which mutual shading and competition for other resources (water, nutrients) prevents forest from developing into even thicker stands. Our hypothesis was that environmental change alters resource limitations, e.g., through an warming-related extension of the growing season, rising CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and its effect on photosynthesis, and altered nutrient inputs from atmospheric deposition. The analysis of long-term forest trends is complicated by the fact that in many regions of the globe, including Switzerland, forest stand dynamics today (at leas partly) reflect the forest use of the past and that these legacy effects play out over multiple decades to even centuries. It is therefore challenging to disentangle drivers of forest change—a chaning environment or recovery from past forest use? Our approach to avoid this complication was to analyse self-thinning trends. They would reflect a change in the “carrying capacity” of a forest stand, after recovery from past forest use, and at a point where dynamics are dominated by (natural) self-thinning process. We thereby achieve an effective separation of recovery from past disturbance vs. shifting maximum carrying capacity. The focus on forests in Switzerland provided a suitable starting point in view of the high-quality forest data from repeated sampling, with oldest data from the 1930s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found a general shift in the self-thinning relationship, pointing to a trend of relieved self-thinning constraints and higher forest carrying capacities &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022AV000859&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Marqués et al., 2023b)&lt;/a&gt; We also found a clear relationship between the self-thinning line and forest stand growth. More vigurously growing stands exhibit a higher carrying capacity, growing into thicker stands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-self-thinning-relationship-and-its-change-over-time-a-and-in-relation-to-stand-growth-b-shown-are-the-numer-of-trees-per-area-y-axis-vs-the-average-size-quadratic-mean-diameter-x-axis-for-individual-forest-plot-observations-points-on-double-logarithmic-scales-the-data-distribution-is-shown-by-insets-figure-from-marqués-et-al-2023bhttpsdoiorg1010292022av000859&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;self-thinning relationship&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/marques23_stl_hu7fb2e4270dee095a0aaf962a04e8683c_272419_9bef46838ce0e6b603803bd0b29a573f.webp 400w,
               /media/marques23_stl_hu7fb2e4270dee095a0aaf962a04e8683c_272419_a167a4a7e4c1eed50fb6e37c2397714b.webp 760w,
               /media/marques23_stl_hu7fb2e4270dee095a0aaf962a04e8683c_272419_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/marques23_stl_hu7fb2e4270dee095a0aaf962a04e8683c_272419_9bef46838ce0e6b603803bd0b29a573f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;376&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Self-thinning relationship and its change over time (a) and in relation to stand growth (b). Shown are the numer of trees per area (y-axis) vs. the average size (quadratic mean diameter, x-axis) for individual forest plot observations (points) on double-logarithmic scales. The data distribution is shown by insets. Figure from &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022AV000859&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Marqués et al., 2023b)&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The empirical forest data analysis was complemented by model simulations. For this, we adopted the BiomeE model and implemented it within our general modelling framework rsofun &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.11.24.568574v3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Stocker et al., 2025a)&lt;/a&gt;. This clarifyied our mechanistic interpretation of observed patterns in the data. The model also simulated an upward shift of the self-thinning relationship (line in figure above) and a positive relationship between growth and biomass changes. However, there is a distinct non-linearity in this relationship, leading to muted changes in biomass stocks (smaller relative enhancement of steady-state biomass stocks than of biomass growth). The degree of this non-linearity is strongly controlled by model assumptions and parameter choices. This work generated two important findings: First, faster tree growth can be expected to drive a sustained C sink in thickening forests despite an acceleration of forest stand dynamics and biomass turnover. Second, the simulation of these dynamics critically depends on poorly constrained model parameters. Our analysis of Swiss forests also sparked several additional works. The non-linearity of relationships between C fluxes and C stocks appeared from our analysis as a key metric describing the (modelled) dynamics of the terrestrial C cycle. This motivated the analysis of linearity of modelled relationships between photosynthesis, growth, and C storage in different plant compartments from outputs of global C cycle models &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.09.01.673458v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Zhang-Zheng et al., 2025)&lt;/a&gt;.  The analysis of &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022AV000859&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Marqués et al., 2023b)&lt;/a&gt; revealed a pattern that could influence the global carbon cycle and the accumulation of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere, if the changes in self-thinning and forest carrying capacity appear generally across forests globally. Therefore, we have gathered data from forests globally and analysed self-thinning trends and quantified respective consequences for the terrestrial C sink (Marqués et al., in prep.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;towards-a-next-generation-vegetation-modelling-framework&#34;&gt;Towards a next-generation vegetation modelling framework&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A unifying aim of the different work strands pursued in the project was to integrate developments into a novel modelling framework. Work was therefore designed to yield new benchmarks and model calibration targets that are systematically being used for extending the model-data integration and all model applications and developments were designed to yield re-usable outputs in the form of successive developments of the open access modelling framework &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17313273&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rsofun&lt;/a&gt; — now integrating the eco-evolutionary optimality-based photosynthesis model (P-model, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.geosci-model-dev.net/13/1545/2020/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al. (2020)&lt;/a&gt;) and the forest dynamics model (BiomeE), used in &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022AV000859&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Marqués et al., 2023b)&lt;/a&gt;. We further developed the code to enable the use of the P-model within BiomeE (yielding ‘BiomeEP’). This constitutes substantial novelty and enabled us to participate in a larger model intercomparison project for vegetation demography models &lt;a href=&#34;https://nph.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/nph.70643&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Eckes‐Shephard et al., 2025)&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17313273&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rsofun&lt;/a&gt; modelling framework is implemented as an R package and is available on the curated central library repository for R packages (CRAN). To mark the release of this package and provide a description of its implementation of model-data integration, we published an article (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.11.24.568574v3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Paredes et al., 2025&lt;/a&gt;, a revised version of this article has been accepted for publication after peer review in &lt;em&gt;Geoscientific Model Development&lt;/em&gt; on 11.11.2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several other works that were carried out over the course of the project MIND further contributed to advancing &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17313273&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rsofun&lt;/a&gt; as a central modelling framework that integrates multiple strands of related research. &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1029/2024MS004789&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Schneider et al., 2025)&lt;/a&gt; demonstrated that the P-model accurately simulates the acclimation and adaptation of the photosyntheis thermal optimum. &lt;a href=&#34;https://nph.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/nph.19208&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Luo et al., 2023)&lt;/a&gt; revealed a systematic reduction of spring photosynthesis rates from ecosystem flux measurements at differen sites and showd how the effect can be represented in photosynthesis models to yield more accurate simulations of springtime CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; assimilation of vegetation in winter-cold climates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also addressed a fundamental question regarding the relation of phenology and photosynthesis that directly relates to assumptions underlying many carbon cycle models, including modelling work in this project. Responding to recently published results and using the P-model in our modelling framework &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17313273&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rsofun&lt;/a&gt;, we showed that autumn leaf phenology (senescence) is delayed or stable despite a general trend of earlier leaf-unfolding in spring and despite higher photosynthetic CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; assimilation in the early season &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-022-01946-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Marqués et al., 2023a)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;outputs&#34;&gt;Outputs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pre-prints-and-submitted-articles&#34;&gt;Pre-prints and submitted articles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2025&#34;&gt;2025&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Helpap, P., Brönnimann, S., Hand, R., Franke, J., and Stocker, B. D.: Are modern droughts unprecedented?, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.22541/essoar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.22541/essoar&lt;/a&gt;, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Zhang-Zheng, H., Arora, V. K., Anthoni, P., Pugh, T. A. M., Jain, A. K., Yuan, W., Malhi, Y., Nabel, J., Goll, D. S., Pongratz, J., Poulter, B., Walker, A. P., Zaehle, S., Knauer, J., Kato, E., Ding, R., Tang, M., Sitch, S., O’Sullivan, M., Terrer, C., Tian, H., Pan, N., Friedlingstein, P., Ito, A., Sun, Q., Decayeux, J., and Stocker, B. D.: Diagnosing linearity along the carbon cascade in terrestrial biosphere models, bioRxiv, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.09.01.673458&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.09.01.673458&lt;/a&gt;, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2024  Stocker, B. D. and Prentice, I. C.: CN-model: A dynamic model for the coupled carbon and nitrogen cycles in terrestrial ecosystems, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.04.25.591063&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.04.25.591063&lt;/a&gt;, bioRxiv, 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Paredes, J. A., Hufkens, K., Marcadella, M., Bernhard, F., and Stocker, B. D.: rsofun v5.0: A model-data integration framework for simulating ecosystem processes, bioRxiv, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.11.24.568574&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.11.24.568574&lt;/a&gt;, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;published-peer-reviewed-articles&#34;&gt;Published peer-reviewed articles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2025-1&#34;&gt;2025&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Eckes-Shephard, A. H., Argles, A. P. K., Brzeziecki, B., Cox, P. M., De Kauwe, M. G., Esquivel-Muelbert, A., Fisher, R. A., Hurtt, G. C., Knauer, J., Koven, C. D., Lehtonen, A., Luyssaert, S., Marqués, L., Ma, L., Marie, G., Moore, J. R., Needham, J. F., Olin, S., Peltoniemi, M., Piltz, K., Sato, H., Sitch, S., Stocker, B. D., Weng, E., Zuleta, D., and Pugh, T. A. M.: Demography, dynamics and data: building confidence for simulating changes in the world’s forests, New Phytologist, p. nph.70643, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.70643&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.70643&lt;/a&gt;, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Schneider, P. D., Gessler, A., and Stocker, B. D.: Global Photosynthesis Acclimates to Rising Temperatures Through Predictable Changes in Photosynthetic Capacities, Enzyme Kinetics, and Stomatal Sensitivity, Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems, 17, e2024MS004 789, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2024MS004789&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2024MS004789&lt;/a&gt;, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Stocker, B. D., Dong, N., Perkowski, E. A., Schneider, P. D., Xu, H., de Boer, H. J., Rebel, K. T., Smith, N. G., Van Sundert, K., Wang, H., Jones, S. E., Prentice, I. C., and Harrison, S. P.: Empirical evidence and theoretical understanding of ecosystem carbon and nitrogen cycle interactions, New Phytologist, 245, 49–68, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.20178&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.20178&lt;/a&gt;, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2024&#34;&gt;2024&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Liu, J., Ryu, Y., Luo, X., Dechant, B., Stocker, B. D., Keenan, T. F., Gentine, P., Li, X., Li, B., Harrison, S. P., and Prentice, I. C.: Evidence for widespread thermal acclimation of canopy photosynthesis, Nature Plants, 1–9, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41477-024-01846-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41477-024-01846-1&lt;/a&gt;, 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Sophia, G., Caldararu, S., Stocker, B. D., and Zaehle, S.: Leaf habit drives leaf nutrient resorption globally alongside nutrient availability and climate, Biogeosciences, 21, 4169–4193, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-4169-2024&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-4169-2024&lt;/a&gt;, 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Tian, D., Yan, Z., Schmid, B., Kattge, J., Fang, J., and Stocker, B. D.: Environmental versus phylogenetic controls on leaf nitrogen and phosphorous concentrations in vascular plants, Nature Communications, 15, 5346, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-49665-4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-49665-4&lt;/a&gt;, 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Kladny, K.-R., Milanta, M., Mraz, O., Hufkens, K., and Stocker, B. D.: Enhanced prediction of vegetation responses to extreme drought using deep learning and Earth observation data, Ecological Informatics, 80, 102 474, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoinf.2024.102474&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoinf.2024.102474&lt;/a&gt;, 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2023&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Keenan, T. F., Luo, X., Stocker, B. D., De Kauwe, M. G., Medlyn, B. E., Prentice, I. C., Smith, N. G., Terrer, C., Wang, H., Zhang, Y., and Zhou, S.: A constraint on historic growth in global photosynthesis due to rising CO2, Nature Climate Change, pp. 1–6, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-023-01867-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-023-01867-2&lt;/a&gt;, 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Marqués, L., Weng, E., Bugmann, H., Forrester, D. I., Rohner, B., Hobi, M. L., Trotsiuk, V., and Stocker, B. D.: Tree Growth Enhancement Drives a Persistent Biomass Gain in Unmanaged Temperate Forests, AGU Advances, 4, e2022AV000 859, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022AV000859&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022AV000859&lt;/a&gt;, 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Peng, Y., Prentice, I. C., Bloomfield, K. J., Campioli, M., Guo, Z., Sun, Y., Tian, D., Wang, X., Vicca, S., and Stocker, B. D.: Global terrestrial nitrogen uptake and nitrogen use efficiency, Journal of Ecology, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.14208&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.14208&lt;/a&gt;, 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Luo, Y., Gessler, A., D’Odorico, P., Hufkens, K., and Stocker, B. D.: Quantifying effects of cold acclimation and delayed springtime photosynthesis resumption in northern ecosystems, New Phytologist, 240, 984–1002, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19208&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19208&lt;/a&gt;, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Giardina, F., Gentine, P., Konings, A. G., Seneviratne, S. I., and Stocker, B. D.: Diagnosing evapotranspiration responses to water deficit across biomes using deep learning, New Phytologist, 240, 968–983, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19197&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19197&lt;/a&gt;, 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Caldararu, S., Rolo, V., Stocker, B. D., Gimeno, T. E., and Nair, R.: Ideas and perspectives: Beyond model evaluation – combining experiments and models to advance terrestrial ecosystem science, Biogeosciences, 20, 3637– 3649, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-20-3637-2023&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-20-3637-2023&lt;/a&gt;, 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Stocker, B. D., Tumber-Dávila, S. J., Konings, A. G., Anderson, M. C., Hain, C., and Jackson, R. B.: Global patterns of water storage in the rooting zones of vegetation, Nature Geoscience, pp. 1–7, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&lt;/a&gt;, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Van Sundert, K., Leuzinger, S., Bader, M. K.-F., Chang, S. X., De Kauwe, M. G., Dukes, J. S., Langley, J. A., Ma, Z., Marïen, B., Reynaert, S., Ru, J., Song, J., Stocker, B., Terrer, C., Thoresen, J., Vanuytrecht, E., Wan, S., Yue, K., and Vicca, S.: When things get MESI: the Manipulation Experiments Synthesis Initiative – a coordinated effort to synthesize terrestrial global change experiments, Global Change Biology, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb&lt;/a&gt;. 16585, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Marqués, L., Hufkens, K., Bigler, C., Crowther, T. W., Zohner, C. M., and Stocker, B. D.: Acclimation of phenology relieves leaf longevity constraints in deciduous forests, Nature Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution, pp. 1– 7, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-022-01946-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-022-01946-1&lt;/a&gt;, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Bloomfield, K. J., Stocker, B. D., Keenan, T. F., and Prentice, I. C.: Environmental controls on the light use efficiency of terrestrial gross primary production, Global Change Biology, 29, 1037–1053, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16511&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16511&lt;/a&gt;, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2022&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Qiu, C., Ciais, P., Zhu, D., Guenet, B., Chang, J., Chaudhary, N., Kleinen, T., Li, X., Müller, J., Xi, Y., Zhang, W., Ballantyne, A., Brewer, S. C., Brovkin, V., Charman, D. J., Gustafson, A., Gallego-Sala, A. V., Gasser, T., Holden, J., Joos, F., Kwon, M. J., Lauerwald, R., Miller, P. A., Peng, S., Page, S., Smith, B., Stocker, B. D., Sannel, A. B. K., Salmon, E., Schurgers, G., Shurpali, N. J., Warlind, D., and Westermann, S.: A strong mitigation scenario maintains climate neutrality of northern peatlands, One Earth, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oneear.2021.12.008&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oneear.2021.12.008&lt;/a&gt;, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Joshi, J., Stocker, B. D., Hofhansl, F., Zhou, S., Dieckmann, U., and Prentice, I. C.: Towards a unified theory of plant photosynthesis and hydraulics, Nature Plants, 8, 1304–1316, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41477-022-01244-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41477-022-01244-5&lt;/a&gt;, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Yu, X., Orth, R., Reichstein, M., Bahn, M., Klosterhalfen, A., Knohl, A., Koebsch, F., Migliavacca, M., Mund, M., Nelson, J. A., Stocker, B. D., Walther, S., and Bastos, A.: Contrasting drought legacy effects on gross primary productivity in a mixed versus pure beech forest, Biogeosciences, 19, 4315–4329, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-19-4315-2022&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-19-4315-2022&lt;/a&gt;, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• McCarthy, M., Meier, F., Fatichi, S., Stocker, B. D., Shaw, T. E., Miles, E., Dussaillant, I., and Pellicciotti, F.: Glacier contributions to river discharge during the current Chilean megadrought, Earth’s Future, n/a, e2022EF002 852, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1029/2022EF002852&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1029/2022EF002852&lt;/a&gt;, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2021&#34;&gt;2021&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Favero,  A.,  Mendelsohn,  R.,  Sohngen,  B.,  and  Stocker,  B.:   Assessing  the  long-term  interactions  of  climate  change  and  timber  markets  on  forest  land  and carbon  storage,  Environmental  Research  Letters,  16,  014 051,  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/abd589&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/abd589&lt;/a&gt;, 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Ma, H., Mo, L., Crowther, T. W., Maynard, D. S., van den Hoogen, J., Stocker, B. D.,Terrer, C., and Zohner, C. M.:  The global distribution and environmental driversof aboveground versus belowground plant biomass, Nature Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution, 5,1110–1122, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-021-01485-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-021-01485-1&lt;/a&gt;, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2020&#34;&gt;2020&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Joos, F., Spahni, R., Stocker, B. D., Lienert, S., Müller, J., Fischer, H., Schmitt, J., Prentice, I. C., Otto-Bliesner, B., and Liu, Z.:  N2O changes from the Last Glacial Maximum  to  the  preindustrial  –  Part  2:  terrestrial  N2O  emissions  and  carbon– nitrogen  cycle  interactions,  Biogeosciences,  17,  3511–3543,  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10&lt;/a&gt;. 5194/bg-17-3511-2020, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Stocker, B. D., Wang, H., Smith, N. G., Harrison, S. P., Keenan, T. F., Sandoval, D., Davis, T., and Prentice, I. C.: P-model v1.0: an optimality-based light use efficiency model for simulating ecosystem gross primary production, Geosci. Model Dev., 13, 1545–1581, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1545-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1545-2020&lt;/a&gt;, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Franklin, O., Cramer, W., Pietsch, S., Prentice, I.C.,Wang Han, Brännström, Å., Dieckmann, U.,Falster, D., Farrior, C., Hofhansl, F., Penuelas, J., Mäkelä, A., Manzoni, S.,  Rebel, K., Rovenskaya, E., Soudzilovskaia, N., Stocker, B. D., Terrer, C., van Bodegom, P., Wright, I., Zaehle, S.: Organizing principles for vegetation dynamics, Nature Plants, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41477-020-0655-x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41477-020-0655-x&lt;/a&gt;, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Peaucelle, M., Janssens, I. A., Stocker, B. D., Descals Ferrando, A., Fu, Y. H., Molowny-Horas, R., Ciais, P., and Peñuelas, J.: Spatial variance of spring phenology in temperate deciduous forests is constrained by background climatic conditions, Nature Communications, 10, 5388, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10&lt;/a&gt;. 1038/s41467-019-13365-1, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;published-data-and-code&#34;&gt;Published data and code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2025-2&#34;&gt;2025&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Stocker, B., Hufkens, K., Bernhard, F., Marqués, L., Arán, P., Maspons, J., Marcadella, M. and Kurth, A., and Peng, Y.: geco-bern/rsofun: rsofun 5.1.0, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17313273&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17313273&lt;/a&gt;, 2025. [R package]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2024-1&#34;&gt;2024&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Bernhard, F., Hufkens, K., Stocker, B., and Gribi, P.: geco-bern/map2tidy: v2.1, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13356532&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13356532&lt;/a&gt;, 2024. [R package]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Stocker, B. D. and Tian, D.: geco-bern/leafnp_data: v1.0: Initial release, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11071944&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11071944&lt;/a&gt;, 2024. [Dataset]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Stocker, B. D. and Tian, D.: geco-bern/leafnp: v1.0: Initial release, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11071816&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11071816&lt;/a&gt;, 2024 [Code]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Stocker, B., Perkowski, E., and Peng, Y.: geco-bern/lt cn review: v2.1 Analysis code for Stocker et al., 2024 (New Phytologist) Empirical evidence and theoretical un- derstanding of ecosystem carbon and nitrogen cycle interactions, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13736727&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13736727&lt;/a&gt;, 2024. [Code]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2023-1&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Peng, Y. and Stocker, B. D.: Yunke Peng et al. Journal of Ecology 2023, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/DOI:10.5281/zenodo.10532099&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/DOI:10.5281/zenodo.10532099&lt;/a&gt;, 2024. [Dataset]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Sundert, K. V., Leuzinger, S., Bader, M. K.-F., Chang, S. X., Kauwe, M. G. D., Dukes, J. S., Langley, J. A., Ma, Z., Marien, B., Reynaert, S., Ru, J., Song, J., Stocker, B. D., Terrer, C., Thoresen, J., Vanuytrecht, E., Wan, S., Yue, K., Geunens, O., Goeminne, G.-J., Torfs, J. R. R., Vrijens, D., and Vicca, S.: MESI: a database of terrestrial global change experiments, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10423853&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10423853&lt;/a&gt;, 2023. [Dataset]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Giardina, F.: fgiardin/fET: Accepted for publication, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8186408&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8186408&lt;/a&gt;, 2023 [Code]
• Marqués, L., Stocker, B., and Hufkens, K.: geco-bern/GFDY: v2.0, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8271848&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8271848&lt;/a&gt;, 2023. [Codę]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2022-1&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Giardina, F., Gentine, P., Konings, A., and Stocker, B.: fET time series, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6885164&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6885164&lt;/a&gt;, 2022. [Dataset]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Stocker, B.: geco-bern/mct: v4.0, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7429129&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7429129&lt;/a&gt;, 2022 [Code]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marqués, L., Stocker, B., and Hufkens, K.: computationales/phenoEOS: v4.0 (v4.0), &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7245870&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7245870&lt;/a&gt;, 2022. [Code]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2021-1&#34;&gt;2021&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Benjamin Stocker, &amp;amp; Koen Hufkens. (2021). rpmodel v1.2.0: R package implementing the P-model (v1.2.0). Zenodo. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773325&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773325&lt;/a&gt; [R package]
• R package rpmodel published also on CRAN
• Stocker, B., Hufkens, K., and Bernhard, F.: geco-bern/cwd: v1.0: Initial release, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14249539&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14249539&lt;/a&gt;, 2024 [R package]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Benjamin Stocker, &amp;amp; Koen Hufkens. (2021). ingestr v1.3: R package for environmental data ingest (v1.3). Zenodo. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5531240&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5531240&lt;/a&gt; [R package]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Theory and data of carbon-nitrogen cycle interactions</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/cnmodel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 13:50:03 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/cnmodel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-does-nitrogen-influence-the-global-carbon-cycle&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How does nitrogen influence the global carbon cycle?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nitrogen is an essential nutrient for plants and is used both in photosynthesis enzymes and for building cell structures. Therefore, plant availability of nitrogen plays an important role in the global carbon cycle and its change under global warming and an increase in atmospheric CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. For example, the question is whether and to what extent nitrogen availability limits the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; fertilization of plant growth. Global models simulate these relationships and therefore require a solid understanding of relevant processes. In our review study (Stocker et al., 2024), we show (i) that these models simulate strongly divergent global carbon balances in recent decades (Fig. 1), (ii) that these divergences are related to different representations of carbon-nitrogen cycle interactions, and (iii) that theoretical foundations from evolutionary ecology enable more robust models that explain essential patterns from empirical analyses and experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-temporal-change-in-the-global-c-sink-over-the-years-1959-2020-from-model-simulations-and-observations-obs-models-are-divided-into-model-types-that-simulate-carbon-and-nitrogen-interactions-cn-and-models-that-only-simulate-the-carbon-cycle-c-model-names-are-given-in-the-legend-this-figure-shows-that-cn-models-diverge-strongly-in-their-simulation-of-the-land-carbon-sink-while-c-models-are-relatively-consistent-with-each-other-but-systematically-overestimate-the-sink-figure-from-stocker-et-al-2024&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;TRENDY C sink&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/sink_trend_trendy_hu169a0d21c952d5d5f48878c75c78ebec_143408_f61e97168fdb5c4d518b9e53d7f7c3d7.webp 400w,
               /media/sink_trend_trendy_hu169a0d21c952d5d5f48878c75c78ebec_143408_3ff34f758fc47da85a978f99011a489d.webp 760w,
               /media/sink_trend_trendy_hu169a0d21c952d5d5f48878c75c78ebec_143408_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/sink_trend_trendy_hu169a0d21c952d5d5f48878c75c78ebec_143408_f61e97168fdb5c4d518b9e53d7f7c3d7.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;590&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Temporal change in the global C sink over the years 1959-2020 from model simulations and observations (Obs.). Models are divided into model types that simulate carbon and nitrogen interactions (CN) and models that only simulate the carbon cycle (C). Model names are given in the legend. This figure shows that CN models diverge strongly in their simulation of the land carbon sink, while C models are relatively consistent with each other, but systematically overestimate the sink. Figure from Stocker et al. (2024).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another study (Stocker &amp;amp; Prentice, 2024), we show how these theoretical foundations can be implemented in a dynamic model of terrestrial carbon and nitrogen dynamics. The foundation of the model is (i) the acclimatization of photosynthesis to the abiotic environment (climate, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) and its implication for nitrogen demand, and (ii) the allocation of assimilated carbon for growth in aboveground biomass (stem, leaves) versus root growth. The model representation of allocation is based on the functional balance approach, which is dynamically simulated in the model as a function of nitrogen, light, and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; availability. With these relatively simple basic assumptions, we can predict both the seasonal plant growth dynamics and the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and nitrogen balance of the ecosystem (Fig. 2), as well as the response of plants to experimentally manipulated CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentration and nitrogen fertilization. Thus, we provide a demonstration of how the core of global vegetation models can be formulated to more reliably simulate global changes in the carbon cycle and thus in the Earth system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;N sinks&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/n_sinks_sources_hu5bbe5ba41921232431f4f9ec0d9c9f6d_118531_3ea58ba7cfcd9fd73e2cb313cc19f92f.webp 400w,
               /media/n_sinks_sources_hu5bbe5ba41921232431f4f9ec0d9c9f6d_118531_74d4401e834323fa540956d3828fea47.webp 760w,
               /media/n_sinks_sources_hu5bbe5ba41921232431f4f9ec0d9c9f6d_118531_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/n_sinks_sources_hu5bbe5ba41921232431f4f9ec0d9c9f6d_118531_3ea58ba7cfcd9fd73e2cb313cc19f92f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;256&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-modeled-seasonal-plant-growth-dynamics-and-the-c-and-nitrogen-n-balance-of-an-ecosystem-figure-from-stocker--prentice-2024&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;C sinks&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/c_sinks_sources_hu99f830e2f24d10e77b169d1820397bff_138753_800ea3fb2c1baee5b3c6b64b404f6399.webp 400w,
               /media/c_sinks_sources_hu99f830e2f24d10e77b169d1820397bff_138753_b33bb73c8a5101fe9dc722334dc4c01a.webp 760w,
               /media/c_sinks_sources_hu99f830e2f24d10e77b169d1820397bff_138753_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/c_sinks_sources_hu99f830e2f24d10e77b169d1820397bff_138753_800ea3fb2c1baee5b3c6b64b404f6399.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;249&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Modeled seasonal plant growth dynamics and the C and nitrogen (N) balance of an ecosystem. Figure from Stocker &amp;amp; Prentice (2024).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocker, B. D., Dong, N., Perkowski, E. A., Schneider, P. D., Xu, H., de Boer, H. J., Rebel, K. T., Smith, N. G., Van Sundert, K., Wang, H., Jones, S. E., Prentice, I. C., and Harrison, S. P.: Empirical evidence and theoretical understanding of ecosystem carbon and nitrogen cycle interactions, &lt;em&gt;New Phytologist&lt;/em&gt;, n/a, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.20178&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.20178&lt;/a&gt;, n.d.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocker, B. D. and Prentice, I. C.: CN-model: A dynamic model for the coupled carbon and nitrogen cycles in terrestrial ecosystems, &lt;em&gt;biorxiv&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.04.25.591063&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.04.25.591063&lt;/a&gt;, 28 April 2024. [pre-print]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Controls on leaf N and P</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/leafnp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 13:50:03 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/leafnp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-do-environmental-factors-and-species-affiliation-influence-nitrogen-n-and-phosphorus-p-concentrations-in-plant-leaves&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(How) do environmental factors and species affiliation influence nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) concentrations in plant leaves?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A widespread assumption is that the nutrient concentration of leaves is mainly determined by species affiliation - a concept known as the “biogeochemical niche hypothesis”. This hypothesis assumes that each plant species occupies a fixed biogeochemical niche with specific N:P ratios. Our study (Tian et al., 2024) challenges this assumption by analyzing the influence of environmental factors on leaf nutrient composition using various statistical and machine learning-based models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-proportion-of-explained-variation-r2-of-environmental-factors-environment-and-species-identity-estimated-with-different-model-types-lmm-linear-mixed-effects-models-rf-random-forest&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Random Forest vs. Linear Mixed Effects model&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/leafp_lmm_rf_hu66b3cef420732c8db6cc4734d682f897_23016_12b39f46f601efb5e441dee396e324a4.webp 400w,
               /media/leafp_lmm_rf_hu66b3cef420732c8db6cc4734d682f897_23016_82881663e997992007323a3fcf3cf621.webp 760w,
               /media/leafp_lmm_rf_hu66b3cef420732c8db6cc4734d682f897_23016_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/leafp_lmm_rf_hu66b3cef420732c8db6cc4734d682f897_23016_12b39f46f601efb5e441dee396e324a4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;691&#34;
               height=&#34;387&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Proportion of explained variation (&lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) of environmental factors (Environment) and species identity, estimated with different model types (LMM: Linear Mixed Effects Models, RF: Random Forest).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About half of the total variation in leaf N and P and in the N:P ratio occurs within species, while environmental variables explain 29 % of the variation in leaf N, 31 % in leaf P and 22 % in the N:P ratio. Nitrogen deposition, atmospheric CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentrations and the temperature of the coldest month are particularly significant. Random forest models identified environmental factors as significant drivers of within-species variation, while linear mixed effects models largely failed to detect these effects. Many species show a high plasticity in their leaf nutrient composition along environmental gradients, indicating a flexible adaptation to different environmental conditions. The results of the study suggest that environmental factors play as important a role as phylogenetic affiliation in determining leaf nutrient composition. We also show that previous interpretations of the data were based on limited statistical methods. This challenges the previous assumption of a fixed biogeochemical niche and emphasizes the importance of phenotypic plasticity of plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;reference&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tian, D., Yan, Z., Schmid, B., Kattge, J., Fang, J., and Stocker, B. D.: Environmental versus phylogenetic controls on leaf nitrogen and phosphorous concentrations in vascular plants, &lt;em&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/em&gt;, 15, 5346, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-49665-4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-49665-4&lt;/a&gt;, 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Forest Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/biomee_forest_inventories/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/biomee_forest_inventories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Forest stands show strong structural heterogeneity in the size distributions of individual trees.
This is driven by growth and mortality and results in allocation of carbon to different biomass pools.
Diverse turnover times of these pools thus affect the net carbon balance of forest ecosystems.
Resolving this heterogeneity of vegetation structure in models of the biosphere is crucial to correctly predict the effect of climate change induced alterations of photosynthetic activity on the ecosystem carbon balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We calibrate the size-structured, mechanistic biosphere model BiomeE with data from forest inventories and flux towers from the PROFOUND project using a Bayesian calibration framework.
Combining these complementary data streams, containing detailed structural information from the forest inventories with observations of carbon and water fluxes from flux towers,
our approach attempts better parametrizations of growth, mortality and carbon allocation at the stand scale, eventually leading to an improved understanding of sensitivities in the forest carbon cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sensing drought stress</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/flue/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 11:57:45 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/flue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Satellite remote sensing data of surface reflectance is widely used to measure vegetation structure and green foliage area and quantify indices such as the NDVI (normalized difference vegetation index). However, effects of abiotic stress (e.g. droughts) and physiological responses are not directly measured or insufficiently captured by such indices and other available surface reflectance-based satellite product. Thus, structural and greenness changes-based diagnosis could lead to an underestimation of the vegetation response to drought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we develop new methods for making more fully use of remote sensing data for monitoring drought stress and plant physiological responses across Central Europe. For this, we&amp;rsquo;re applying machine learning on satellite spectral information, using the target (fLUE) in supervised machine learning algorithms as an estimate of the physiological (only) response to water stress, developed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://nph.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/nph.15123&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al., 2018 &lt;em&gt;New Phytologist&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The effectiveness of this metric in detecting early physiological drought impacts is  evaluated against the widely used vegetation greenness indices (NDVI and EVI) across Central Europe.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Droughts in the last millennium</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/lastmillennium_drought/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 11:57:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/lastmillennium_drought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Land processes governing global water cycling and energy fluxes play an integral role in land-climate interactions. By assessing temporal changes in atmospheric demand (potential evapotranspiration, PET) and supply (precipitation, P) over land, we can gain valuable insights into drought dynamics. Changes in past drought dynamics have previously been studied in specific regions as global observations and paleoclimate proxies are scarce. A global comprehension of the natural variability of droughts and the impacts of external forcings is largely missing. We aim to fill this gap by assessing the development of drought variability throughout the last millennium, including attributing changes to internal variability and external forcings and investigating changes in extreme event distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Ensemble mean potential cumulative water deficit (PCWD) values for the year 1420.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/lastmillennium_drought_hu401a14fdcee016c423edcd5fa5f4f287_394244_298a70424b6d2d7176ed2e92cf342de6.webp 400w,
               /media/lastmillennium_drought_hu401a14fdcee016c423edcd5fa5f4f287_394244_ca05eecb8f7a2d2c51b9359bf84d7151.webp 760w,
               /media/lastmillennium_drought_hu401a14fdcee016c423edcd5fa5f4f287_394244_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/lastmillennium_drought_hu401a14fdcee016c423edcd5fa5f4f287_394244_298a70424b6d2d7176ed2e92cf342de6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;456&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ensemble mean potential cumulative water deficit (PCWD) values for the year 1420.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use output from the medium sized ensemble Modern Era SIMulations (ModE-SIM), which simulate the past 600 years of global climate (Hand et al., 2023). The simulations, divided into two epochs (1420-1849, 1850-2009), are initialized separately to account for decreasing uncertainty in radiative forcings as we approach modern times. Potential cumulative water deficit (PCWD) is calculated from the model output and used as drought metric, as it incorporates atmospheric demand (PET) and supply (P). Daily precipitation is used for calculation so the timing of precipitation events can be included, which allows for drought event definition based on the water balance. The calculation follows the cumulative water deficit algorithm implemented in the cwd package for R (Stocker, 2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For analysis, global PCWD and annual maximum PCWD time series are calculated by gridcell for all 60 ensemble members. To investigate changes over the simulated period, trend and low-frequency variability are assessed. Further, forced versus unforced variability are separated and analysed. Extreme value analysis of PCWD annual maxima is carried out for each gridcell, globally. This also allows us to situate recent droughts in the statistical context established from large ensemble simulations covering 600 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this research hopes to enhance our understanding of global preindustrial drought characteristics, including its simulated natural variability and developments in a warming world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is carried out as part of a MSc thesis and early results will be presented at the ZHydro – “Missing links in drought research” conference in early March 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hand, R. et al. (2023) ‘ModE-Sim – a medium-sized atmospheric general circulation model (AGCM) ensemble to study climate variability during the modern era (1420 to 2009)’, Geoscientific Model Development, 16(16), pp. 4853–4866. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-16-4853-2023&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-16-4853-2023&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Stocker. (2021). cwd v1.0: R package for cumulative water deficit calculation (v1.0). Zenodo. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5359053&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5359053&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sensing drought stress</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/drone_msi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 11:57:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/drone_msi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The extreme summer droughts across Central Europe (i.e., 2003, 2015, and 2018), driven by anthropogenic climate change, emphasized the urgency of understanding and predicting ecosystem responses to extreme droughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water limitation during severe drought limits photosynthesis and respiration by closing stomata, induces xylem cavitation, and reduces plant carbon balance, which leads to seasonal decreases in productivity and long-term increases in tree vulnerability to major disturbances and mortality. These physiological responses to drought events not only depend on their timing, i.e. recurrence and duration, but also on their geography (landscape-scale heterogeneity). For example, large gradients in soil depth, slope, and exposition in mountainous landscapes can therefore cause differential vegetation responses to drought across scales of 10^1^-10^4^ m m. Combining both vegetation (spectral and thermal) indices, and a highly variable geography, offers a non-destructive and rapid method for investigating plant physiological processes under a wide range of drought stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To investigate landscape-scale heterogeneity of drought impacts, the study is carried out in two sites in Valais, Switzerland, with different elevations, soil and plant rooting depths, slopes, and various species exhibiting varying responses to drought stress. Both sites are part of a larger tree monitoring network and provide co-located plant and soil-point measurements of water stress. This study maps temporal variations and landscape-scale heterogeneity in vegetation water stress using UAV-based multispectral remote sensing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing an optimality model for evapotranspiration</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/etmodel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 11:57:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/etmodel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Evapotranspiration (ET) is the second-largest water flux on land and influences the carbon cycle. When the soil is dry, plants close their stomata to prevent water loss and the risk of hydraulic failure, thus limiting carbon assimilation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Modeled and observed latent energy (LE) flux, after calibration at site FR-Pue.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/etmodel_hu2271e33f07c2462b575b6ac6f931a751_345045_edd16c89f9f2972a75a2dfaf30c08572.webp 400w,
               /media/etmodel_hu2271e33f07c2462b575b6ac6f931a751_345045_16e174afed91ea21d1a74095ffdb186a.webp 760w,
               /media/etmodel_hu2271e33f07c2462b575b6ac6f931a751_345045_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/etmodel_hu2271e33f07c2462b575b6ac6f931a751_345045_edd16c89f9f2972a75a2dfaf30c08572.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;380&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modeled and observed latent energy (LE) flux, after calibration at site FR-Pue.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ET can be calculated on daily scale using the Priestly-Taylor (PT) equation (Priestley &amp;amp; Taylor, 1972). However, the PT equation assumes plants&amp;rsquo; stomata to be always open. This leads to an unrealistic representation of the water cycle. The Penmann-Monteith (PM) equation overcomes this problem by explicitly considering vegetation structural properties and how the vegetation activity and stomatal conductance affect ET (Monteith, 1972). This provides a link for using an eco-evolutionary optimality model (the P-model, Stocker et al., 2020) for stomatal regulation and photosynthesis for modelling ET and thus coupling water and carbon fluxes around the dynamic response of plants to the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we incorporate a representation of ecosystem water fluxes based on the PM equation into the P-model for simulating coupled gross primary production (GPP) and ET. We quantify how the coupled treatment of water and carbon fluxes improves the simulation of daily ET and GPP, by comparing to measurements from a worldwide network of eddy-covariance flux towers (FLUXNET) (Pastorello et al., 2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we quantify the role of spatially variable rooting zone water storage capacity for acurately capturing GPP and ET under dry conditions. This is important because during drought days, plants rely on water stored beneath the soil to sustain their activity. The maximum amount of water stored in soils depends on the soils&amp;rsquo; properties and is highly variable in space. For this reason, most of the models consider only the top 2 meters of soil or ignore spatial variations in rooting depth and the rooting zone water storage capacity. Recently, a new estimation of the soil water holding capacity has been made (Stocker et al., 2023). This new estimation will shed new light on vegetation activity during dry periods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monteith, J. L.: Solar Radiation and Productivity in Tropical Ecosystems, Journal of Applied Ecology, 9, 747–766, 1972.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pastorello, G., Trotta, C., Canfora, E., Chu, H., Christianson, D., Cheah, Y.-W., Poindexter, C., Chen, J., Elbashandy, A., Humphrey, M., Isaac, P., Polidori, D., Reichstein, M., Ribeca, A., van Ingen, C., Vuichard, N., Zhang, L., Amiro, B., Ammann, C., Arain, M. A., Ardö, J., Arkebauer, T., Arndt, S. K., Arriga, N., Aubinet, M., Aurela, M., Baldocchi, D., Barr, A., Beamesderfer, E., Marchesini, L. B., Bergeron, O., Beringer, J., Bernhofer, C., Berveiller, D., Billesbach, D., Black, T. A., Blanken, P. D., Bohrer, G., Boike, J., Bolstad, P. V., Bonal, D., Bonnefond, J.-M., Bowling, D. R., Bracho, R., Brodeur, J., Brümmer, C., Buchmann, N., Burban, B., Burns, S. P., Buysse, P., Cale, P., Cavagna, M., Cellier, P., Chen, S., Chini, I., Christensen, T. R., Cleverly, J., Collalti, A., Consalvo, C., Cook, B. D., Cook, D., Coursolle, C., Cremonese, E., Curtis, P. S., D’Andrea, E., da Rocha, H., Dai, X., Davis, K. J., Cinti, B. D., Grandcourt, A. de, Ligne, A. D., De Oliveira, R. C., Delpierre, N., Desai, A. R., Di Bella, C. M., Tommasi, P. di, Dolman, H., Domingo, F., Dong, G., Dore, S., Duce, P., Dufrêne, E., Dunn, A., Dušek, J., Eamus, D., Eichelmann, U., ElKhidir, H. A. M., Eugster, W., Ewenz, C. M., Ewers, B., Famulari, D., Fares, S., Feigenwinter, I., Feitz, A., Fensholt, R., Filippa, G., Fischer, M., Frank, J., Galvagno, M., et al.: The FLUXNET2015 dataset and the ONEFlux processing pipeline for eddy covariance data, Sci Data, 7, 225, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-020-0534-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-020-0534-3&lt;/a&gt;, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Priestley, C. H. B. and Taylor, R. J.: On the Assessment of Surface Heat Flux and Evaporation Using Large-Scale Parameters, Monthly Weather Review, 100, 81–92, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-0493%281972%29100&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-0493(1972)100&lt;/a&gt;&amp;lt;0081:OTAOSH&amp;gt;2.3.CO;2, 1972.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocker, B. D., Wang, H., Smith, N. G., Harrison, S. P., Keenan, T. F., Sandoval, D., Davis, T., and Prentice, I. C.: P-model v1.0: an optimality-based light use efficiency model for simulating ecosystem gross primary production, Geoscientific Model Development, 13, 1545–1581, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1545-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1545-2020&lt;/a&gt;, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocker, B. D., Tumber-Dávila, S. J., Konings, A. G., Anderson, M. C., Hain, C., and Jackson, R. B.: Global patterns of water storage in the rooting zones of vegetation, Nat. Geosci., 1–7, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&lt;/a&gt;, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forest thickening trends</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/stl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 11:57:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/stl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tree growth has increased globally over the last decades but the implications for long-term carbon storage in forests remain unknown. This project aims to investigate whether enhanced tree growth drives persistent biomass increases in different regions, particularly in mature forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enhanced tree growth and stand-level biomass are often linked with a simultaneous increase in density-driven mortality and a reduction in tree longevity. Identifying empirical evidence regarding the balance between these processes is challenging due to the confounding effects of stand history, management, and environmental changes. In this project, we evaluate the link between growth and biomass via the negative relationship between average tree size and stand density (tree number per area).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find increasing stand density for a given mean tree size in unmanaged closed-canopy forests in Switzerland over the past six decades and a positive relationship between tree growth and stand density across forest plots—qualitatively consistent with our simulations using a mechanistic, cohort-resolving ecosystem model (BiomeE). Model simulations show that, in the absence of other disturbances, enhanced tree growth persistently increases biomass stocks despite simultaneous decreases in carbon residence time and tree longevity. Our analyses reconcile reports of growth-induced reductions of tree longevity with model predictions of persistent biomass increases, and with our finding of trends toward denser forests in response to growth—also in mature stands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project has been published in &lt;em&gt;AGU Advances&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1029/2022AV000859&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Marqués et al. (2023)&lt;/a&gt;. After having established methods in Swiss forests, we are currently working to expand the research to other regions and forest biomes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phenology and photosynthesis</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/pheno/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 11:57:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/pheno/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Compared to spring phenology, autumn phenology trends are less distinct, and the magnitude of changes is smaller. This is partly due to multiple confounding factors influencing end-of-season (EOS) dynamics. This project investigates the relationship between autumn phenology and photosynthesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings show that increased photosynthesis does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; lead to earlier leaf shedding in autumn. While a short-term (inter-annual) relationship exists—likely driven by variations in spring phenology and constrained leaf longevity—this pattern does not hold at decadal scales or across spatial gradients. This challenges the interpretation of a recent study by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abd8911&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zani et al. (2020)&lt;/a&gt; on the drivers of autumn phenology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than being driven by carbon sink saturation (i.e., plants ceasing activity once sufficient carbon has been assimilated), long-term trends in climate and rising CO2 levels enable plants to extend their growing season. This allows them to overcome leaf-longevity constraints, meaning that an earlier leaf-out trend does not necessarily result in earlier leaf-off. Instead, the opposite is observed—both in long-term temporal trends and spatial patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project has been published in &lt;em&gt;Nature Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-022-01946-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Marqués et al. (2023)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenness of Swiss Forests</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/greenness_chforests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 13:50:03 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/greenness_chforests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent extreme droughts have caused significant damage to forests across Switzerland and neighbouring regions. Identifying where and when climate extremes impact forest health is crucial for understanding their severity and developing early-warning systems. Remote sensing offers a valuable tool for detecting vegetation stress, as drought-induced tree mortality and premature defoliation appear as negative anomalies (browning) in vegetation indices such as NDVI. However, reliably identifying these anomalies in large, noisy Earth Observation (EO) datasets remains a major challenge. Additionally, distinguishing drought-related browning from other disturbances like late frost, deforestation, or storms requires additional advancements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/dimpeo_hu0ec28758adc0aa72adfb3f3c8e134989_7811718_bb529b14b314cb66f07f039a1a0ace03.webp 400w,
               /media/dimpeo_hu0ec28758adc0aa72adfb3f3c8e134989_7811718_8d5a097a50d98d76e257fc19df93ce4d.webp 760w,
               /media/dimpeo_hu0ec28758adc0aa72adfb3f3c8e134989_7811718_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/dimpeo_hu0ec28758adc0aa72adfb3f3c8e134989_7811718_bb529b14b314cb66f07f039a1a0ace03.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;510&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project focuses on developing robust anomaly detection methods for high-resolution (20 m) Sentinel-2 EO time series data to map and quantify browning impacts on Swiss forests. We have developed two complementary approaches for detecting NDVI anomalies: a neural network-based method and a quantile random forest model. Both methods estimate a normal NDVI range by accounting for seasonal, spatial, and environmental variability, allowing us to flag pixels with significant deviations. One of the approaches has been deployed in a web application to provide a user-friendly interface for visualising detected anomalies across Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next steps include clustering detected anomalies into events and identifying their environmental drivers. We will continue to update our web application with advances in anomaly detection and monitoring. Our aim is to inform forecasting and early-warning systems as well as forest management strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecological data assimilation</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/diego/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 11:57:26 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/diego/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In several projects, we are working towards assimilating diverse data into mechanistic ecosystem models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, we are using forest inventory data, in combination with eddy covariance flux measurements from an intensive monitoring site in Switzerland (&lt;a href=&#34;http://sites.fluxdata.org/CH-Lae/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lägern&lt;/a&gt;) for calibrating our model (rsofun with LM3-PPA, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://geco-group.org/data_code/index.md&#34;&gt;Data and code&lt;/a&gt;) using Bayesian statistical methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A MSc thesis by Ana Roldan is scheduled to start in November 2021 that extends this model-data integration framework. The research question of this thesis will be to investigate feedbacks between photosynthesis and growth, and in particular whether cold-limitation on growth feeds back on photosynthesis and thus induces a temperature-driven sink limitation in forests. To investigate this, we are using data from the intensive monitoring sites at &lt;a href=&#34;http://sites.fluxdata.org/CH-Lae/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lägern&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://sites.fluxdata.org/CH-Dav/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Davos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With planned research, we are aiming to extend model-data integration on the basis of diverse ecological data further. The aim is to accurately simulate impacts of drought and heat stress on CO2 assimilation, transpiration, tree growth, and mortality. Using complementary observations and mechanistically accounting for the links between processes will yield new insights - key for forecasting climate extreme event impacts in Swiss (and other) forests.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimality and plant hydraulics</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/jaideep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 11:57:05 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/jaideep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an important step for developing theory for how plant hydraulics determine stomatal regulation and photosynthetic capacity in response to water stress. The research led by Dr. Jaideep Joshi, IIASA, Austria, is published as a pre-print on BiorXiv (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.17.423132&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Joshi et al. 2020&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model presented here offers a solution to resolve measurable plant hydraulic traits withing the theoretical approach for eco-evolutionary optimality implemented by the P-model (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1545-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al., 2020 &lt;em&gt;GMD&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cold acclimation effects on photosynthesis</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/photocold/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 11:56:58 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/photocold/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ecosystem-level photosynthesis (gross primary production: GPP) can be predicted using remotely sensed information on vegetation cover, local measurements of solar radiation and relatively simple models for the efficiency of photosynthesis (Ryu et al., 2019; Stocker et al., 2019). But one aspect of model-data mismatch stands out: The early-season increase in GPP is typically simulated to be around a month too early at some sites but not at others (Fig. 1). It will be your challenge to find out why and how to resolve this model deficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/photocold_hub128e3b1275bc36b0488c5c647e87e67_632868_b12c5c8465ded379588c92035450b8fe.webp 400w,
               /media/photocold_hub128e3b1275bc36b0488c5c647e87e67_632868_22f8c4bffd2d8c33da79d1e7a70e04b4.webp 760w,
               /media/photocold_hub128e3b1275bc36b0488c5c647e87e67_632868_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/photocold_hub128e3b1275bc36b0488c5c647e87e67_632868_b12c5c8465ded379588c92035450b8fe.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;304&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fig. 1 Mean seasonal cycle of GPP aggregated for 14 sites where without early season overestimation of modelled GPP (a) and 13 sites with an apparent overestimation of early season modelled GPP (b).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hypothesis that may explain this phenomenon is that the photosynthetic apparatus is acclimated to the risk of frost damage in early spring, caused by conditions of low temperature and simultaneously high solar radiation. To prevent excessive light harvesting, photoprotective mechanisms are deployed by plants and lead to reduced photosynthetic carbon assimilation, and hence GPP. At locations with relatively mild winters and limited risk of frost, photoprotection may be less prevalent and photosynthesis rates are high already in the early season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using ecosystem flux data in combination with our photosynthesis model to understand and resolve its ominous early season GPP bias at some sites in some years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research is led by Dr. Yunpeng Luo, a postdoc in my group and co-supervised by Prof. Arthur Gessler, WSL Birmensdorf.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning for GPP</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/mlflx/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 11:56:58 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/mlflx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Machine learning (ML) models are widely used to predict gross primary production (GPP) from ecosystem flux measurements, yet most ignore key temporal dependencies such as thermal acclimation, soil moisture stress, and cold acclimation. These factors influence photosynthesis over time, but many ML models treat GPP observations as independent, potentially limiting their accuracy and generalizability. While process-based models incorporate known physiological mechanisms, they often struggle with flexibility. This project compares a mechanistic photosynthesis model (P-model), a standard ML model (MLP), and a recurrent neural network (LSTM) to assess how well they capture temporal patterns and generalize across ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results (see figure below) show that both ML models outperform the process-based approach. The LSTM effectively captures seasonal dependencies and generalizes well to moist, seasonal sites. However, errors increase under extreme drought, particularly in evergreen forests where water stress effects are harder to detect. The LSTM performs better than the MLP in arid regions, suggesting that temporal memory enhances GPP predictions in water-limited conditions. However, performance remained highly variable in arid regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/mlflx_hu86522dede40294bb942d126d0d60a145_182244_5d0d24d273fab457473db1fe17fa7126.webp 400w,
               /media/mlflx_hu86522dede40294bb942d126d0d60a145_182244_d3af32c49f5e5edcda6e7437aec01115.webp 760w,
               /media/mlflx_hu86522dede40294bb942d126d0d60a145_182244_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/mlflx_hu86522dede40294bb942d126d0d60a145_182244_5d0d24d273fab457473db1fe17fa7126.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;566&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As climate change intensifies water stress, improving GPP models is increasingly important. Our findings highlight the potential of recurrent neural networks for capturing long-term environmental influences but also reveal challenges in arid regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results of this study will be presented at EGU 2025: Session: AS3.44 – Understanding feedbacks between greenhouse gas exchange processes and climate variability using in situ observations, remote sensing, and machine learning&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photosynthese und Spätfrost</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/photocold_d/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 11:56:58 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/photocold_d/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Die Kohlenstoffaufnahme von Wäldern in unseren Breiten ist stark an die saisonalen Schwankungen von Sonnenlicht und die Phänologie gekoppelt. Sobald im Frühling die Sonneneinstrahlung zunimmt und Blätter ausgetrieben werden, nimmt die Aufnahme von CO2 durch die Photosynthese rasch zu. Wir konnten zeigen, dass diese Zunahme an verschiedenen Standorten stark verzögert ist. Trotz rasch ansteigender Sonneneinstrahlung und grüner Vegetation, verzögert sich der saisonale Anstieg der CO2-Aufnahme an bestimmten Standorten um mehrere Wochen. Wir fanden heraus, dass diese Verzögerungen damit zu tun haben, dass an diesen Standorten Spätfrost besonders häufig auftritt – in Nordamerika und Regionen mit kontinentalem Klima, weniger aber in Regionen mit temperiertem, maritimem Klima, z.B. in Nordwesteuropa. Tiefe Temperaturen und hohe Sonneneinstrahlung kann für die Blattphysiologie schädlich sein. Die verzögerte Re-aktivierung der Photosynthese an diesen Standorten ist wahrscheinlich eine Anpassung zur Vermeidung von schädlichen meteorologischen Bedingungen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/photocold_hub128e3b1275bc36b0488c5c647e87e67_632868_b12c5c8465ded379588c92035450b8fe.webp 400w,
               /media/photocold_hub128e3b1275bc36b0488c5c647e87e67_632868_22f8c4bffd2d8c33da79d1e7a70e04b4.webp 760w,
               /media/photocold_hub128e3b1275bc36b0488c5c647e87e67_632868_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/photocold_hub128e3b1275bc36b0488c5c647e87e67_632868_b12c5c8465ded379588c92035450b8fe.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;304&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fig. 1 Saisonale Schwankung der CO2 Aufnahme durch die Photosynthese. Unterschieden sind (b) Daten von 14 Standorten, an welchen eine verspätete Zunahme der Photosynthese in Vergleich des zu erwartenden Flusses (rot) beobachtet wird (Beobachtungen schwarz). In (a) ist die mittlere jährliche Schwankung an 13 Standorten gezeigt, wo dieses Phänomen nicht auftritt.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;publizierte-studie&#34;&gt;Publizierte Studie&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luo, Y., Gessler, A., D’Odorico, P., Hufkens, K., &amp;amp; Stocker, B. D. (2023). Quantifying effects of cold acclimation and delayed springtime photosynthesis resumption in northern ecosystems. New Phytologist, 240(3), 984–1002. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19208&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19208&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DGVM linearity</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/dgvmlin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 11:56:38 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/dgvmlin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This research is led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.geog.ox.ac.uk/graduate/research/hzhang.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Huanyuan Zhan&lt;/a&gt;, PhD student under the main supervision of Prof. Yadvinder Malhi at the University of Oxford, GB. I designed this study and am collaborating closely with Huanyuan on this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many processes that determine the links between C (input) fluxes and C pool sizes in DGVMs are formulated in a linear way, or at least in such a way as to imply &amp;ldquo;linear&amp;rdquo; model behavior. As a consequence, the relative change in fluxes should be equal to the relative change in pool size. Such model formulations are also termed as &amp;ldquo;source-driven&amp;rdquo;. In contrast, &amp;ldquo;sink-driven&amp;rdquo; would imply that it&amp;rsquo;s not the (input) fluxes that determine the change in pool sizes, but other limiting factors that are independent of input fluxes. This has also been formulated as a fundamental critique in the way current DGVMs are conceived and thus, at least partly, predetermine their projected land C balance changes in climate change scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is: How close are models actually from being fully sink-driven? Or in other words: How linear is their dynamics?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DGVMs have evolved over several generations, starting from C-only models with a big-leaf representation and average individuals in a stand, to models that represent a coupled C-nutrient cycling, and now to models that combine explicit representations of forest stand dynamics with biochemical cycling. All these modifications should increase the importance of feedbacks within the system that leads to deviations from a linear, strictly source-driven behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;preliminary-results&#34;&gt;Preliminary results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/img/dgvmlin.png&#34; alt=&#34;Relatinship of the relantive enhancement in NPP versus the relative enhancement in GPP, derived from CO2-only simulations of a set of Dynamic Global Vegetation Models. This shows a point density of data points representing individual gridcells of all models pooled. Their clustering around the 1:1 line indicates linearity in the relationship between GPP and NPP and implies a constant ratio of NPP:GPP.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Relatinship of the relantive enhancement in NPP versus the relative enhancement in GPP, derived from CO2-only simulations of a set of Dynamic Global Vegetation Models. This shows a point density of data points representing individual gridcells of all models pooled. Their clustering around the 1:1 line indicates linearity in the relationship between GPP and NPP and implies a constant ratio of NPP:GPP.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rooting zone water storage capacity</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/rootingdepth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 11:56:38 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/rootingdepth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A pre-print is published on BiorXiv: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460332&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stocker et al. (2021)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global maps of estimated rooting zone water storage capacity and rooting depth is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5515246&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link my vEGU2020 presentation on this project &lt;a href=&#34;https://presentations.copernicus.org/EGU2020/EGU2020-7019_presentation.mp4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rooting depth governs plants&amp;rsquo; access to water during dry (rain-free) periods and is thus a key variable determining the sensitivity of transpiration and carbon assimilation to soil moisture drought and land-climate coupling during drought and heat events. Plant rooting depth variations of two orders of magnitude have been recorded across the globe and a substantial portion of this variation appears within species and functional groups. This suggests that plant rooting depth is a relatively plastic “trait” that may adjust to the local environment and soil hydrology and possibly also to temporally changing climatic conditions. Yet, plant rooting depth is commonly treated as a fixed parameter in global vegetation and climate models, specified for each plant functional type. How can respective trait flexibility be introduced in such models?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approaches to explain these large variations have focussed on the depth of the local water table as a constraint on the maximum rooting depth (Fan et al., 2017), on the mean seasonality and synchrony of precipitation and radiation (Gao et al., 2014; Schenk et al., 2005), or on optimality principles for balancing the trade-offs between the benefits of deep rooting and their associated costs (carbon used for root construction and respiration and maintaining water transport along the entire soil-root-leaf pathway) (Kleidon and Heimann, 1998; Schymanski et al., 2009).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we follow the approach by Gao et al. (2014), assuming that plants’ rooting depth is adjusted to sustain cumulative water deficits (precipitation minus evapotranspiration: P - ET) of a magnitude, corresponding to an event with a return period of N years, where N is a global constant. The water deficit is determined using daily reanalysis data of precipitation, while ET is estimated from remotely sensed vegetation cover and observed radiation, and from simulated stomatal responses to observed vapour pressure deficit across the globe for the past 35 years. Cumulative water deficits are translated into a “soil drying depth” using information on soil texture and its estimated water holding capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results reveal a global pattern of plant rooting depth, adjusted to the apparent cumulative water deficit during rain-free periods, peaking at intermediate aridity, where dry periods are long, radiation is high, and vegetation cover is substantial. A comparison to biome-level distributions of observed rooting depths indicates that the control by the cumulative water deficit, embodied in our model, is a powerful driver of variations between biomes. Shallowest rooting depths are observed and modelled in boreal forests and alpine meadows, while deepest rooting is observed and modelled in xeric forests. Stomatal response to dry conditions appears to be an important mechanism that mitigates the necessity for deep rooting, particularly in broadleaved tropical and temperate forests. Our analysis also revealed challenges in bridging the scales of observations and our global-scale model, possibly due to small-scale heterogeneity in soil water availability driven by the topographic setting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New constraints on terrestrial photosynthesis</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/terrphoto/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 09:36:01 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/terrphoto/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Photosynthesis of the terrestrial biosphere drives the land carbon cycle. For example, year-to-year variations in terrestrial photosynthesis are the dominant cause for year-to-year changes in land carbon uptake and the rate of increase in atmospheric CO2. Understanding terrestrial photosynthesis is thus important for understanding the fate of anthropogenic CO2 emissions and their effect on driving climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, terrestrial photosynthesis cannot be measured directly. Most available estimates are based on remote sensing observations of the vegetation cover, combined with models for the efficiency by which absorbed light is used for carbon assimilation. Recently, new methods have been developed to use alternative remotely sensed observations (e.g., sun-induced fluorescence) to estimate terrestrial photosynthesis. Also Dynamic Global Vegetation Models (DGVMs) provide estimates of terrestrial photosynthesis, but they don&amp;rsquo;t use remotely sensed observations directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/img/terrphoto.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Above: (left) spatial distribution of annual mean sun-induced fluorescence (SiF), a proxy for GPP; (right) spatial distribution of annual total GPP, mean across multiple remote sensing-based models. This illustrates the inconsisten spatial distribution (particularly the tropics-extratropics gradient) of remote sensing-based GPP estimates.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research in our group has revealed that these approaches yield inconsistent estimates in terms of (i) the spatial distribution of photosynthesis rates and (ii) the magnitude of year-to-year variability. The challenge that you will address in this project is to find new constraints to resolve this inconsistency. The use of atmospheric CO2 measurements holds great promise as a constraint, but requires an estimate of the net carbon balance (including gains by photosynthesis and losses by respiration and disturbance). In this project, you will establish this link. You will develop a reduced-complexity representation of the terrestrial carbon balance, based on DGVM outputs and a pulse-response representation of terrestrial carbon storage. This will be used to &amp;ldquo;translate&amp;rdquo; remote-sensing based terrestrial photosynthesis estimates into implied effects on atmospheric CO2 and its spatial and year-by-year variations. Like this, we will be able to subject  the contrasting remote sensing based estimates of terrestrial photosynthesis to a new test and find out which ones are more wrong than others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis is a great starting point for working with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere and modelling. Experience with working with R, Python or other data science tools are an advantage. You may start as soon as you like.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Landcover6K model intercomparison</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/hololu_lc6k/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 13:51:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/hololu_lc6k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;title: Landcover6K
summary: An example of using the in-built project page.
date: &amp;ldquo;2016-04-27T00:00:00Z&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;optional-external-url-for-project-replaces-project-detail-page&#34;&gt;Optional external URL for project (replaces project detail page).&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;external_link: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://stineb.github.io/holoLU_lc6k/%22&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://stineb.github.io/holoLU_lc6k/&#34;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;image:
caption:
focal_point: Smart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;icon: twitter
icon_pack: fab
name: Follow
url: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/georgecushen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/georgecushen&lt;/a&gt;
url_code: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://stineb.github.io/holoLU_lc6k/%22&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://stineb.github.io/holoLU_lc6k/&#34;&lt;/a&gt;
url_pdf: &amp;quot;&amp;rdquo;
url_slides: &amp;quot;&amp;rdquo;
url_video: &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;slides-optional&#34;&gt;Slides (optional).&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;associate-this-project-with-markdown-slides&#34;&gt;Associate this project with Markdown slides.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;simply-enter-your-slide-decks-filename-without-extension&#34;&gt;Simply enter your slide deck&amp;rsquo;s filename without extension.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;eg-slides--example-slides-references-contentslidesexample-slidesmd&#34;&gt;E.g. &lt;code&gt;slides = &amp;quot;example-slides&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; references &lt;code&gt;content/slides/example-slides.md&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;otherwise-set-slides--&#34;&gt;Otherwise, set &lt;code&gt;slides = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;!-- slides: example --&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carbon-water coupling across scales</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/project/soilm_global/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 11:46:14 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/project/soilm_global/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary-of-our-research&#34;&gt;Summary of our research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41561-019-0318-6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;new paper published in &lt;em&gt;Nature Geoscience&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (view it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41561-019-0318-6.epdf?author_access_token=BGVLWmElvocQ1pE62QCTW9RgN0jAjWel9jnR3ZoTv0OyhWonkp6GWFgymRIu-XiwzwuX2z2Y2LYuKXkpzWa99FZSDRcHEaLWYZDRcaio1Et-soqame00xLPa-MvXHz_RVj455cGThJ-86CjHA2XimQ%3D%3D&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), we identified a common bias in different state-of-the-art satellite-based estimates of terrestrial photosynthesis, and found that this bias is closely related to droughts and their apparent impact on the functioning of vegetation. In other words, common satellite-based vegetation monitoring methods underestimate the impact of droughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the implications of this bias for our understanding of the terrestrial C cycle and its year-to-year variability? We investigated this question using a new global implementation of the P-model (open-access code available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stineb/sofun&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Our results suggest that accurately capturing soil moisture stress in photosynthesis modelling is  crucial for estimating the year-to-year variability in vegetation productivity and the impacts of drought extreme events. Not capturing this effect accurately leads to a substantial underestimation of this variability and to a systematic underestimation of drought extreme event impacts on vegetation productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in our simulations, the locally strong soil moisture effect on vegetation productivity and its variability does not translate into a similarly strong water-control on the global-scale variability in terrestrial gross primary productivity. This is due to the compensating effects of different continents that are not synchronously drought-stressed and tend to compensate each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In view of a recent study by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-018-0424-4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Humphrey et al. (2018)&lt;/a&gt; who found a clear relationship between terrestrial water storage and the atmospheric CO2 growth rate, this raises a fundamental question about the evident water-carbon coupling at the global scale: Is it  an apparent phenomenon where terrestrial water storage is a proxy for some other factor that controls vegetation functioning? Or are we missing some element of plant access to water that has a longer memory and stronger year-to-year variability, so that the simulated compensating effects from different continents that we found would no longer neatly compensate each other at the global scale? This is an exciting lead for future research&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-links&#34;&gt;Further links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://geco-group.org/post/soilm_global/&#34;&gt;blogpost&lt;/a&gt; written for &lt;a href=&#34;https://natureecoevocommunity.nature.com/channels/521-behind-the-paper&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nature Ecology and Evolution - Behind the Paper&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://geco-group.org/files/pressrelease_soilm_global.pdf&#34;&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt; written in collaboration with Natalie Sanders, Imperial College&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-and-code&#34;&gt;Data and code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model output data from site-scale and global P-model simulations are available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/1423484#.XIJNAlNKjOQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code for the entire analysis and producing figures is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/2543324#.XIJNTVNKjOQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt; and on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stineb/soilm_global&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;. Compile (knit) RMarkdown file &lt;code&gt;knit_soilm_global.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; for a full reproduction of results or &lt;code&gt;si_soilm_global.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; for re-creating the Supplementary Information to our paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
